for letting me interview you okay and
can you say a little bit about how the
Masters and holistic science at Omaha
College started when did you first think
about setting up a program like that
well it started when we developed the
capacity for people to get credits for
attending short courses three-week
courses we did that through the
University of Plymouth and that was
about let's see 13 years ago or so so
people could come on a regular short
course and get 10 masters level credits
for that work um and we did that for
about 3 3 years or so that it was very
successful we got quite a few people
doing the credits I was the academic
tutor along with petia Sullivan from the
University premise and others from the
immersive chemist and it worked really
well for the next the next phase with
Aussie to expand it and to do a fully
blown master's degree of our own and
then I remember one day Ventana Shiva
brought Brian Goodwin here to give a
talk and I was really really delighted
by his talk and he loved the college and
gradually we realized that we could
start a master's degree with him so
that's that's how it got going really
and when can you sort of give a little
bit of a historic background of when the
first mussels were set up in hope sort
of developed over the years yeah I think
we're in our ninth year so this next
intake will be the 10th so it was 1998
we start out with two students a
professor of dentistry from South Africa
and a Japanese student as two students
um yeah we just got going really it was
very experimental
we had a module structure all approved
by the University of Plymouth with five
modules over four months and then
dissertation and then two optional
courses from the short course program
and it seemed to work very well and the
next year it went up
we have the next year six I think and it
just kept going up and going out so we
hit the ceiling around 12 or 13 and
going back a little bit further how did
you first come to Omaha College and
you've been here since the beginning
yeah I'm one of the founders of it young
how did I get here well it was thanks to
Tibetan monk they got here because I've
been in Costa Rica for two years
teaching ecology the National University
and then I came out to England for a
little while I was heading back to Costa
Rica but I was a member of a Buddhist
group at Oxford and this Tibetan monk
came to their group who wanted to come
down to Devon so I agreed to be a
chauffeur and I came down here and heard
about this nascent Institute here then
called it shumar College at the time the
doctor was wanting to set up and I came
over and talked to say teach and John
Lane and bears other people and they
said well my become the ecologist of
this new Institute and James Lovelock is
going to be the first teacher that all
we had already been arranged and that
got me excited president I read his book
and was very interested in his work and
then they decided to call it the
Schumacher College which I thought was a
really brilliant name so I decided that
it was my destiny to come here so I gave
up on the game back to Costa Rica and
came here instead and then began my
friendship with James Lovelock which has
lasted all that time yeah that's the
next thing that I wanted to and talk to
you about you've collaborated with James
Lovelock and he's been a mentor and
friend for many years he say a little
bit more about what you've been working
on and what impact he's had on your
thinking and mmm-hmm well there's a
surface superficial answer and a deep
answer the superficial answer is
straightforward he gave me a computer
and he gave me the code in basic for
daisyworld
and he said just go and play with this
because I taught myself
computer programming that
I was doing my doctorate so I was
familiar with how to structure computer
programs although I'm not a
mathematician but I was able to see how
data world works I had the equations
there are six equations and I could see
how he translated them into code it was
very very interesting to see how that
worked how the numerical integration
happens anyway so I thought wow this is
very interesting stuff and then I hit on
a few ideas for experiments for making
them they've evolved more ecologically
realistic so he worked on that together
for about five years or so and to
publish two papers on it so I used to go
to Kumail a lot and we were you know
talking to him on the phone quite a bit
these are in the days when really no one
no one else much was interested in Gaia
he was felt quite isolated I think and
he was quite excited that there was
someone an opposite of the biologist as
he said it was interested in in his work
later on lots of other people came
people from the Met Office and Tim
Linton and other people joined in who
have you know really very very able in
this domain anyway so I did a lot of
work with him on that but that's the
superficial level of work but the deeper
thing is hard to pin down actually
but it's that he's got a pen he's a very
special personality and he's got a
gentleness and a softness but also
almost an indigenous understanding of
what Gaia is poetic almost any mystic
understanding and all of that came
through to me just through being with
him walking around his land talking to
him he sort of gave me a lot of
nurturing a tremendous generosity and a
mentoring that I received from him which
was more just on an intellectual level
it was um I think curative level really
it's like being with the label wires
English Aboriginal elder and so I've
absorbed that quite a lot and it comes
through it the way I talk about guy
so do you think that he holds a sort of
scientific view of Gaia and also
something that is deeper that is almost
like a spiritual and philosophical yeah
I think so he wouldn't like me to say
this mm-hmm but yeah he's got a
brilliant scientific understanding of
Gaia but he will say himself he's very
intuitive I think he is very intuitive I
mean he's he's a great inventor and his
intuitions sorry his inventions come out
of intuition normally he sort of works
on the problem he doesn't get an answer
and works and it works and then at 3:00
in the morning he wakes up with the
answer and he talks a lot about
intuition and the importance of
intuition and the importance of the
unconscious mind so he's aware of these
things
so yes it's both they profound
scientifically but also he who are a
strong intuitive understanding of a kind
of nature and that's what makes them
unusual I think and very special and I
think people feel that when they see him
giving a talk while I'm meeting in
person that there's something unusual
here that most scientists don't have
there's an extra dimension to this
person that you don't find in most
scientists mainly intellectuals and